Guide to the University Theatre Records 1925-2009
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
University Theatre Records
1925-2009
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
RG 180
Oregon State University. Dept. of Speech Communication.
6 cubic feet 6 boxes, including 2 oversize boxes, and 3 map folders
1 microfilm reel
The University Theatre Records document dramatic stage productions at Oregon State University beginning in the 1920s and consist predominantly of play files and theater posters.
Historical Note:
Dramatic productions began at Oregon Agricultural College in the 1890s; the Mask and Dagger Club was formed in 1912 "to encourage and promote dramatic work." A theater program was formally established in 1920 as part of a new Public Speaking and Dramatics Department (now the Speech Communication Department). Dramatic productions were presented at the Majestic Theater in downtown Corvallis and a small theater in Benton Hall until 1950 when a campus structure was remodeled into the Mitchell Playhouse. The University Theatre moved to Withycombe Hall in 1991 after Mitchell Playhouse was declared unsafe.
The University Theatre Records document drama productions at Oregon State University beginning in the 1920s. The bulk of the collection consists of play files for individual plays and posters publicizing performances and annual theater seasons. About 40 of the posters are original painted artwork. The records also include programs, scripts, publications, and materials documenting the summer theater program in the early 1970s.
Collection is open for research.
The records are arranged in 9 series: I. Play Files, 1928-1965; II. Play Lists, 1929-1988; III. Scripts of Plays, 1931-2009; IV. Summer Theater, 1972-1973; V. Programs, circa 1925-2009; VI. National Collegiate Players Fraternity (Drama Honorary), circa 1925; VII. Posters, 1935-2009; VIII. Plans for Stage Switchboard, 1949; and IX. Publications, 1999-2009.
List of posters available online.
Materials in the collection were received in numerous transfers from 1970 through 2009.
Additions to the collection are expected.
The C.B. Mitchell University Theater Scrapbooks document theater productions at Oregon State College during the 1920s through early 1950s. Materials pertaining to drama activities prior to 1920 are available in the Feronian Literary Society and Mask and Dagger Club Records (RG 042). Extensive photographs of the dramatic productions at Oregon State comprise the University Theater Photographs (P 112). Some additional information about theater and dramatics at Oregon State is part of the Speech Communication Department Records (RG 181) as well as the Memorabilia Collection.
Mask and Dagger Club (Oregon Agricultural College); Oregon State Agricultural College. Dept. of Public Speaking and Dramatics.; Oregon State University. Dept. of Theatre.; Oregon State College. Dept. of Speech.; Oregon State University. Dept. of Speech.
College and school drama, American--Oregon--Corvallis.; Drama--Study and teaching--Oregon--Corvallis.
Posters.
Colleges and Universities; Performing Arts; Student Life; Oregon; Corvallis
- Play Files, 1928-1965; Series I
  The Play Files document the promotion, rehearsals, and performances of stage productions by the University Theatre and include rehearsal schedules; information pertaining to scenery and costume rentals, ticket sales, and attendance; programs and publicity; invoices and budgets; newspaper clippings; correspondence; and seating charts. The files are arranged chronologically. Play files for 1928-1950 are only available on microfilm; files for later productions are available in original paper form.
  - The Kelly Kid, the Monkey's Paw, and For Distinguished Service, May 4, 1928; 1 (Box reel 1)
  - The Devil in the Cheese, December 7-8, 1929 (Reel reel 1)
  - Hell Bent for Heaven, May 23-24, 1930; 2 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Dover Road, November 22-23, 1930; 3 (Reel reel 1)
  - Cock Robin, Feb. 18-19, 1930; 4 (Reel reel 1)
  - Merchant of Venice, March 6-7, 1931; 5 (Reel reel 1)
  - Youngest, May 1931; 6 (Reel reel 1)
  - Beyond the Horizon, April 1932; 7 (Reel reel 1)
  - Little Prison and The Land of Heart's Desire, Nov. 17, 1932; 8 (Reel reel 1)
  - There's Always Juliet, Nov. 24-26; 9 (Reel reel 1)
  - Wurzle-Flummery and 'Op- 'o-Me-Thumb, February 16, 1933; 10 (Reel reel 1)
  - Death Takes a Holiday, March 9-11, 1933; 11 (Reel reel 1)
  - Rose O' Plymouthtown, May 4-6, 1933; 12 (Reel reel 1)
  - Summer Session Play, July 21, 1933; 13 (Reel reel 1)
  - Bread, December 1933; 14 (Reel reel 1)
  - Both Your Houses, March 9-10, 1934; 15 (Reel reel 1)
  - Career for Mother, The Finger of God, and The Mayor's House, November 23; 16 (Reel reel 1)
  - No More Frontier, May 1-2, 1935; 17 (Reel reel 1)
  - Tables and Chairs, Are Men Superior, and Society Column, July 29, 1935; 18 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Kelley Kid and The Clock Struck One, November 21,1935; 19 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Climbers and Maizie, February 6, 1936; 20 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Man who Married a Dumb Wife, March 11, 1936; 21 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Man Who Married a Dumb Wife and Cabbages, July 24, 1931 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Streets of New York, December 13-14, 1935; 22 (Reel reel 1)
  - Three Cornered Moon, March 6-7, 1936; 23 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Ivory Door, May 8-9, 1936; 24 (Reel reel 1)
  - Mansions and Lavender and Red Pepper, 25 (Reel reel 1)
  - Laburnum Grove, Dec. 3-4, 1936; 26 (Reel reel 1)
  - Grandma-Old Style, Dec. 10, 1936; 27 (Reel reel 1)
  - R.U.R., March 5-6, 1937; 28 (Reel reel 1)
  - Aladdin, April 19, 1937; 29 (Reel reel 1)
  - Ladies of the Jury, May 7-8, 1937; 30 (Reel reel 1)
  - First Lady, Dec. 10-11, 1937; 31 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Ship, Feb. 11-12, 1938; 32 (Reel reel 1)
  - School for Scandal, May 6-7, 1938; 33 (Reel reel 1)
  - Act Your Age, July 25, 1938; 34 (Reel reel 1)
  - High Tor, Dec. 2-3, 1938; 35 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Monkey's Paw, Cabbages, and For Distinguished Service, Feb. 14, 1939; 36 (Reel reel 1)
  - George and Margaret, March 3-4, 1939; 37 (Reel reel 1)
  - Tovarich, May 12-13, 1939; 38 (Reel reel 1)
  - Cross My Heart, July 24, 1939; 39 (Reel reel 1)
  - Mystery at Greenfingers, Dec. 1-2, 1939; 40 (Reel reel 1)
  - Spring Dance, March 1-2, 1940; 41 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Precious Stream, May 1940; 42 (Reel reel 1)
  - Stage Door, May 23-24, 1940; 43 (Reel reel 1)
  - Sunday Costs 5 Pesos and The Wonder Hat, 1940; 44 (Reel reel 1)
  - Going Places, July 29, 1940; 45 (Reel reel 1)
  - Susan and God, Dec. 6-7, 1940; 46 (Reel reel 1)
  - What a Life, Dec. 12-13, 1940; 47 (Reel reel 1)
  - Lillion, March 7-8, 1940; 48 (Reel reel 1)
  - You Can't Take it with You, April 5, 1941; 49 (Reel reel 1)
  - In a House Like This, May 9-10, 1941; 50 (Reel reel 1)
  - Night Must Fall, May 22-24, 1941; 51 (Reel reel 1)
  - So This is Hollywood, July 28, 1941; 52 (Reel reel 1)
  - Our Town, Nov. 12-13, 1941; 53 (Reel reel 1)
  - George Washington Slept Here, Dec. 5-6, 1941; 54 (Reel reel 1)
  - Ever Since Eve, July 20, 1942; 55 (Reel reel 1)
  - Glamour Preferred, May 8-9, 1942; 56 (Reel reel 1)
  - Goodbye Again, April 16-18, 1942; 57 (Reel reel 1)
  - Dark Victory, march 6-7, 1942; 58 (Reel reel 1)
  - Arsenic and Old Lace, Dec. 3-4, 1942; 59 (Reel reel 1)
  - Fly Away Home, March 4-5, 1943; 60 (Reel reel 1)
  - Craig's Wife, May 7-8, 1943; 61 (Reel reel 1)
  - Young April, Dec. 9-11, 1943; 62 (Reel reel 1)
  - Personal Appearance, March 17-18, 1944; 63 (Reel reel 1)
  - Letters to Lucerne, Dec. 7-8, 1944; 64 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Torchbearers, March 1-2, 1945; 65 (Reel reel 1)
  - Mrs. Partridge Presents, May 11-12, 1945; 66 (Reel reel 1)
  - Snafu, Dec. 6-7, 1945; 67 (Reel reel 1)
  - Outward Bound, March 7-8, 1946; 68 (Reel reel 1)
  - Holiday, May 10-11, 1946; 69 (Reel reel 1)
  - Blithe Spirit, Nov. 15-16, 1946; 70 (Reel reel 1)
  - Dear Ruth, Dec. 5-6, 1946; 71 (Reel reel 1)
  - Purple Doorknob, China Pig, and Wisdom Teeth, June 6, 1946; 72 (Reel reel 1)
  - East Lynne, Feb. 7-8, 1947; 73 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Little Foxes, March 6-7, 1947; 74 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Haunted House, May 23-24, 1947; 75 (Reel reel 1)
  - I Remember Mama, May 8-10, 1947; 76 (Reel reel 1)
  - Foot-Loose, July 22, 1947; 77 (Reel reel 1)
  - Apple of His Eye, Nov. 14-15, 1947; 78 (Reel reel 1)
  - Claudia, Dec. 4-5, 1947; 79 (Reel reel 1)
  - Joan of Lorraine, Feb. 13-14, 1948; 80 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Scarecrow, March 4-5, 1948; 81 (Reel reel 1)
  - State of the Union, May 6-8, 1948; 82 (Reel reel 1)
  - Squaring the Circle, May 4-5, 1948; 83 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Cat and the Canary, July 20, 1948; 84 (Reel reel 1)
  - A Murder has Been Arranged, Nov. 12-13, 1948; 85 (Reel reel 1)
  - Papa is All, Dec. 2-3, 1948; 86 (Reel reel 1)
  - Room Service, Feb. 18-19, 1949; 87 (Reel reel 1)
  - MacBeth, March 3-4, 1949; 88 (Reel reel 1)
  - Years Ago, May 5-7, 1949; 89 (Reel reel 1)
  - Dulcy, May 20-21, 1949; 90 (Reel reel 1)
  - Storm in a Teacup, Nov. 10-12, 1949; 91 (Reel reel 1)
  - Thunder Rock, Dec. 1-3, 1949; 92 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Bat, Feb. 16-18, 1950; 93 (Reel reel 1)
  - Androcles and the Lion, March 2-4, 1950; 94 (Reel reel 1)
  - Hay Fever, May 4-6, 1950; 95 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Far Off Hills, May 25-27, 1950; 96 (Reel reel 1)
  - Green Pastures, Dec. 7-9, 1950; 97 (Reel reel 1)
  - The Milky Way, February 15-17, 1951 (Box 1)
  - There Shall be No Night, March 1-3, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Heaven Can Wait, May 24-26, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Berkeley Square, May 3-5, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Arsenic and Old Lace, November 1-3, 1951 (Box 1)
  - The Winslow Boy, November 28-29 and December 1, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Born Yesterday, February 7-9, 1952 (Box 1)
  - The Cradle Song, March 6-8, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Autumn Garden, May 1-3, 1952 (Box 1)
  - June Moon, May 22-24, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Harvey, November 6-8, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Double Door, December 4-6, 1952 (Box 1)
  - The Male Animal, February 12-14, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Our Town, March 5-7, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Two Blind Mice, April 30 and May 1-2, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Playboy of the Western World, May 21-23, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Good-Bye My Fancy, November 5-7, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth the Queen, December 3-5, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Blithe Spirit, February 11-13, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Taming of the Shrew, March 4-6, 1954 (Box 1)
  - The Man Who Came to Dinner, April 29-30 and May 1, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Ten Little Indians, May 20-22, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Good House Keeping, August 4-6, 1954 (Box 1)
    Summer session.
  - Affairs of State, November 4-6, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Heart Break House, December 2-4, 1954 (Box 1)
  - The Country Girl, February 10-12, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Sabrina Fair, March 3-5, 1955 (Box 1)
  - My Three Angels, May 5-6, 1955 (Box 1)
  - The Torchbearers, May 26-28, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Bell, Book, and Candle, November 3-5, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Night Must Fall, December 1-3,1955 (Box 1)
  - The Late George Apley, February 9-11, 1956 (Box 1)
  - The Glass Menagerie, March 1-3, 1956 (Box 1)
  - The Solid Gold Cadillac, May 3-5, 1956 (Box 1)
  - The Curious Savage, Mary 24-26, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Time Out for Ginger, August 1956 (Box 1)
  - Present Laughter, November 1-3, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Oklahoma, November 28-30, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Life with Father, February 7-9, 1957 (Box 1)
  - The Desperate Hours, February 28 and March 1-2, 1957 (Box 1)
  - The Guest Cottage, May 23-25, 1957 (Box 1)
  - The Parlor Story, July 31 and August 1, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Teahouse of the August Moon, November 7-9, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Antastasia, May 2-4, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Dial "M" for Murder, December 5-7, 1957 (Box 2)
  - The Crucible, February 13-15, 1958 (Box 2)
  - The Fourposter, March 6-8, 1958 (Box 2)
  - The Late Christopher Bean, May 1-3, 1958 (Box 2)
  - See How They Run, May 22-24, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Lo and Behold, August 6-7, 1958 (Box 2, 5)
  - Ladies in Retirement, November 6-8, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Mary of Scotland, December 4-6, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Rain, February 12-14, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Visit To A Small Planet, March 5-7, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Life With Mother, April 30, May 1-2, 1959 (Box 2)
  - The Lady Chooses, May 21-23, 1959 (Box 2)
  - A Room Full of Roses, August 5-6, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Witness for the Prosecution, November 5-7, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Annie Get Your Gun, December 1-5, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Third Best Sport, February 11-13, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Antigone, March 3-5, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Mister Roberts, May 5-7, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Be Your Age, August 3-4, 1960 (Box 2)
  - The Importance of Being Earnest, May 26-28, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Girls in 509, November 3-5, 1960 (Box 2)
  - The Seed and the Thorn, December 1-3, 1960 (Box 2)
  - The Great Diamond Robbery, February 9-11, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Separate Tables, March 2-4, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Picnic, May 4-6, 1961 (Box 2)
  - She Stoops to Conquer, May 25-27, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Nude with Violin, July 27-29, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Three Men on a Horse, November 2-4, 1961 (Box 2)
  - The Knight of the Burning Pestle, November 30, December 1-2, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Inherit the Wind, February 8-10, 1962 (Box 2)
  - The Great Sebastians, March 1-3, 1962 (Box 2)
  - The Diary of Anne Frank, May 3-5, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Arms and the Man, May 24-26, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Pool's Paradise, August 2-3, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Speaking of Murder, November 1-3, 1962 (Box 2)
  - R.U.R., November 29-30, December 1, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Jacques Cartier, December 7, 1962 (Box 2)
  - A Streetcar Named Desire, February 7-9, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Critic's Choice, February 28, March 1-2, 1963 (Box 2)
  - The Great White Swan, March 6, 1963 (Box 2)
  - The Silver Whistle, May 2-4, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Shadow and Substance, May 23-25, 1963 (Box 2)
  - An Evening of Albee, August 1-2, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Happiest Millinaire, November 7-9, 1963 (Box 2)
  - The Aspern Papers, December 5-7, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Six Characters in Search of an Author, February 6-8, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Private Lives, March 5-7, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Little Mary Sunshine, April 30, Map 1-2, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Come Back, Little Sheba, May 21-23, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Kind Sir, August 5-6, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Hamlet, December 1-5, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Papa is All, February 11-13, 1965 (Box 3)
  - A Man for All Seasons, March 4-6, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Mary, Mary, May 13-15, 1965 (Box 3)
  - The Seven Year Itch, November 4-6, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Seasons of 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - One Acts, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
- Play Lists, 1929-1988; Series II (Box 3)
  Series II consists of lists of plays performed by the the University Theatre.
- Scripts of Plays, 1931-2009; Series III
  Series III includes scripts of several plays performed at Oregon State in the 1930s and in 2009 with annotations and performance notes.
  - The Two Vagabonds, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Without First Aid, 1934 (Box 3)
  - School for Scandal, 1938 (Box 3)
  - The Laramie Project: Ten Years Later, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Shakespeare's Journey, 2009 (Box 3)
- Summer Theater, 1972-1973; Series IV (Box 3)
  Series IV documents the Summer Theater Program in 1972 and 1973 and includes budgets and funding requests, brochures, newspaper clippings, reports, correspondence, and records of funding provided by the Oregon Arts Commission.
- Programs, circa 1925-2009; Series V
  Series V includes programs of theater performances at Oregon State, primarily during the 1920s-1930s and 1990s-2000s.
  - 1926-1943 (Box 4)
  - Undated, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 4)
  - The Mikado, 2008 (Box 4)
  - The Laramie Project and My Name is Rachel Corrie, 2009 (Box 4)
  - 1994-2007, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - One Act Festivals, 1995-2004 (Box 4)
  - Playbill for Streets of New York, 1935 (Box 5)
- National Collegiate Players Fraternity (Drama Honorary), circa 1925; Series VI (Box 5)
  Series VI consists of the charter certificate for the Oregon State College chapter of the National Collegiate Players drama honorary society.
- Posters, 1935-2009; Series VII; 2 oversize boxes and 3 map folders
  Series VII consists of more than 200 posters promoting individual University Theatre productions as well as theater seasons. Most of the posters are printed items smaller than 20x24 inches. The series also includes about 40 original painted posters (about 30 inches by 45 inches) for productions in the 1950s and 1960s. Several of these posters include 8x10 b/w portrait photographs of lead cast members. A list of posters included in the collection is available online.
- Plans for Stage Switchboard, 1949; Series VIII; 1 map folder (*)
  Designed by Northern School Supply of Portland, Oregon; 1 sheet.
- Publications, 1999-2009; Series IX
  The Publications include the annual newsletter for theater arts at Oregon State and several issues of the Northwest Theater Review, a regional journal of works by or about Northwest theater scholars and practitioners, published by the Northwest Drama Conference.
  - Northwest Theater Review, 2004-2007 (Box 4)
    Edited by George Caldwell, OSU Speech Communications professor. An article in the 2005 issue by Marion O. Rossi, Jr., and Charlotte J. Headrick examines Shakespeare plays staged at Oregon State University.
  - Entra'acte, 1999-2009 (Box 4)
    Newsletter of the theater arts at Oregon State University, published annually in the fall.